<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be enquired of, in the Kynges Maiesties visitacion.</title>
            <author>Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1547</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00118</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10116.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112543</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844389</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844389</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12852</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00118)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12852)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 11:9, 97:3, 2284:1b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be enquired of, in the Kynges Maiesties visitacion.</title>
                  <author>Church of England.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII).</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Richardus Grafton regis impressor excudebat. Cumpriuilegio ad imprimendum solum.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1547?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An edition of "Articles to be enquyred of, in the kynges majesties visitacion" (STC 10114). Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a⁴ b² .</note>
                  <note>Copy at reel 11:9 identified on film as STC 10116.</note>
                  <note>Copy at reel 2006: bound and filmed following STC (2nd ed.) 10091, and preceding STC (2nd ed.) 13640.5.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="articles_of_visitation">
            <pb facs="tcp:12852:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ARTICLES to be enquired of, in the Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Maieſties Viſitacion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, whether that the Biſhop, Archedeacons, and other, hauynge iuriſdiccion Eccleſiaſticall, haue cauſed onely to be ſong or ſayde the Engliſh Proceſſion in their Cathedrall churche, &amp; other churches of their Dioceſſe.</p>
            <p>Item, whether your Biſhop, Chauncelor, Commiſſarie, Archedeacon, or Officiall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe and light in excommunicating of men, for a litle Lucre.</p>
            <p>Item, whether they or any of them, for one mans treſpaſſe, haue taken away from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the whole pariſhioners, their diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uice, as for violatyng &amp; ſuſpending the churche yeardes and ſuche lyke.</p>
            <p>Item, whether thei do take exceſſiue ſomes of money for conſecratinge agayne either of the church yeardes, or of any other ornamentes for the vſe of alters, or of belles, where is no nede of conſecracion, but is ſuperſticiouſe and lucra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue.</p>
            <p>Item, whether that they or any of them take any great exactions, for inſtitucions, induccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s aſſignations of pencions, or for any other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Eccleſiaſticall.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12852:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->Item, whether they do lightly call any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons before them, ex officio, and put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their purgacion, without vrgent ſuſpicion or infamy proued,</p>
            <p>Item, whether the Biſhop haue not prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched without diſſimulacion, agaynſte the vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped power of the Biſhop of Rome, and ſetfurth the kynges of Maieſties Iuriſdiction to bee the onely ſupreme power in all his realmes and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions.</p>
            <p>Whether the Biſhop haue perſonally prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in any of your churches, or any wher with in this dioceſſe, and how ofte in the yere.</p>
            <p>Item, whether he and hys officers haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly executed for their part, our late Kynges Iniunctions and his letters miſſiues, for a due order in the religion of Chriſte, and cauſed the ſayde Iniunctions and letters, to be diligently put in execution thorough his Dioceſſe.</p>
            <p>Item, whether he hath learned and diſcrete officers vnder him, that do without any reſpect of perſones punyſhe ſuche crymes, as appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to Eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction.</p>
            <p>Item, whether he or any of his officers, do ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke any money or other gifte, to hyde &amp; cloke ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultery, or any other notorious vyce, that ought by them to be puniſhed.</p>
            <p>Item, if any commutacion of penaunce ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ben made to a pecuniary ſome, to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe theſame hathe bene conuerted, and what good dedes hathe bene done with theſame, and
<pb facs="tcp:12852:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
ſpecify theſame deedes.</p>
            <p>Item whether the biſhop hath ſuche chaplai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes aboute hym, as been hable to preache thee woorde of God, and do theſame purely and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, and howe ofte in the yere, how many they be, and what be their names.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Tem whether Perſones, Vicars &amp; Curates, and euery of them, haue iuſtly and truely without diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, preached agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the vſurped power, and pretenſed aucthoritie &amp; iuriſdiccion of the Biſhop of Rome.</p>
            <p>Item, whether thei haue preached and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the Kynges Maieſties power, auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and preeminence, is wythin thys Realme and the dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of theſame, the moſte ſupreme and higheſt vnder God.</p>
            <p>Item, whether any perſone hath by writyng, Cyphryng, Printyng, preachyng, or teachynge, dede, or acte, obſtinately holden and ſtand with, to extoll, ſet furthe, maintein or defende, the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, iuriſdiccion or power of the Biſhop of Rome, or of his Sea, heretofore claimed and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped: or by any pretenſe, obſtinatly or malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted any thyng for the extollyng of the ſame, or any parte therof.</p>
            <p>Item, whether they haue declared to theyr Pariſhioners the articles concernyng the abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion of certayn ſuperfluous holy dayes, and dooen their indeuoure, to perſwade their ſayed
<pb facs="tcp:12852:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->
Pariſhioners to kepe and obſerue theſame arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles inuiolably, and whether any of thoſe abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated daies hath ſithens theſayed abrogacion, been kept as holy dayes, contrary to theſaid ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and by whoſe occaſion they were ſo kept.</p>
            <p>Whether there do remayne not taken doune in your Churches, Chapelles, or els where, any miſuſed Images, with Pilgrimages, clothes, ſtones, ſhoes, offerynges, kiſſynges, Candelſtic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, trindilles of waxe, and ſuche other like, and whether there do remayne not delayed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, any Shrines, coueryng of Shrines, or any other monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Idolatrie, Superſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Hypocryſy.</p>
            <p>Whether thei haue not diligently taught v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Sondaies and holy daies, their Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners, and ſpecially y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> youth, their Pater no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, the Articles of oure faythe, and the Tenne commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes in Engliſh, and whether thei haue expounded and declared the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of theſame.</p>
            <p>Whether thei haue diligently, duely &amp; reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, miniſtered the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes in their cures.</p>
            <p>Whether ſuch beneficed men, as be lawfully abſent from their benefices, doo leaue their cure to a rude and vnlearned perſone, and not to an honeſt, well learned and expert Curate.</p>
            <p>Whether thei haue prouided &amp; laied in ſome conuenient place of the churche where thei haue cure, a bible of the largeſt volume in Engliſhe.</p>
            <p>Whether Perſones, Vicars, Curates, Chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery
<pb facs="tcp:12852:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->
Prieſtes, and other ſtipendaries be commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haunters and reſorters to Tauernes and Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, geuing themſelfes to exceſſiue drinkyng riotyng, and plaiyng at vnlawfull games, and apply not themſelfes chiefly to the ſtudy of ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, teachyng of youthe, or ſome other honeſt and Godly exerciſe.</p>
            <p>Whether thei be reſident vpon their benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and kepe hoſpitalitie or no: and if thei be ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or kepe no hoſpitalitie, whether thei do make due diſtribucion emonges the poore Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners or no.</p>
            <p>Whether they hauing yerely to diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall promocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s an. C.<abbr>l.</abbr> do not find co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petenly one ſcolar in any vniuerſitie, or at ſome gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer ſcole, and for aſmany. C.<abbr>l.</abbr> as euery of them may diſpend, ſo many ſcolars likewiſe be founde by them, and what be their names that thei ſo find.</p>
            <p>Whether thei kepe their Chauncelles, Recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Vicarages, and all other houſes appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng to them, in due reparacions.</p>
            <p>Whether thei haue euery lent, required their Pariſhioners in their confeſſion, to recite their Pater noſter, tharticles of our faith, &amp; the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne commaundementes in Engliſhe.</p>
            <p>Whether thei haue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſailed or moued theyr Pariſhioners, rather to praye in a toungue not knowen, then in Engliſhe, or to put their truſte in any preſcribed numbre of prayers, as in ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng ouer a numbre of beades or other like.</p>
            <p>Whether thei haue preached, or cauſed to bee
<pb facs="tcp:12852:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
preached purely and ſyncerely the word of God &amp; the faith of chriſt in euery of their cures, euery quarter of the yere once at the leaſt: Exhortyng their Pariſhioners to the workes commaunded by ſcripture, and not to workes diuiſed by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes phantaſies.</p>
            <p>Whether in their ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, they haue exhorted the fathers and Mothers, Maſters, and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of youth, to bryng theim vp in ſome verte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtudy or occupacion.</p>
            <p>Whether thei haue exhorted the people to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the kynges Maieſtie and his officers and to charitie and loue, one to another.</p>
            <p>Whether thei haue moued the people to read and heare the ſcripture in Engliſhe, &amp; haue not diſcoraged theim from readyng and hearyng of theſame, ſuche as be not prohibited ſo to do.</p>
            <p>Whether thei haue declared to their pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners, that thei ought to knowe and vnderſtande the Pater noſter, the Articles of our faith, &amp; ten co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes in Engliſhe, before thei ſhould receiue the bleſſed Sacrament of the aulter.</p>
            <p>Whether thei haue taught the people the true vſe of Images, whiche is onely to put theim in remembraunce of the Godly and vertoous lifes of them that thei do repreſent: and haue taught that if theſayed people vſe the Images for any other purpoſe, thei committe Idolatrie, to the greate daunger of their ſoules.</p>
            <p>Whether they haue declared, and to theyr wittes and power haue perſwaded the people,
<pb facs="tcp:12852:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
that the maner and kynde of faſtynge in Lent &amp; other dayes in the yere, is but a meere poſytyue lawe, and that therfore all perſons hauing iuſie cauſe of ſickenes, or neceſſitie, or beyng licenced by the kynges Maieſtie, maye temperately eate all kyndes of meate without grudge or ſcruple of conſcience.</p>
            <p>Whether your Parſonnes, Vicars, and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates haue ſhewed and declared vnto you, thee true vſe of ceremonies, that is to ſay: That they be no workers, nor woorkes of ſaluacyon, but onely outwarde ſignes and tookens to put vs in remembraunce of thynges, of higher perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Whether thei haue admitted any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in their cures, not beynge lawfully licenced thereunto, or haue refuſed or repelled ſuche too preache, as haue bene ſo licenced.</p>
            <p>Whether they, which haue ſpoken and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red any thyng for the ſettingfurth of pilgrima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, fayned reliques, images, or any ſuch ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticion, haue not openly recanted theſame.</p>
            <p>Whether they haue one boke or regiſtre ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uefely kept, wherin they write the daye of euery weddynge, chriſteninge, and buriynge.</p>
            <p>Whether the kinges Iniunccions wer quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly red or not.</p>
            <p>Whether they haue declared to theyr pary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyoners, that ſayncte Markes daye, and the euens of the abrogated holy dayes, ſhould not be faſted.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12852:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->Whether the knollynge at the Aues bee vſed.</p>
            <p>Whether they haue the proceſſion boke in Engliſhe, &amp; in their proceſſions vſe none other Letany, but that, whiche is ſetfurthe in theſame boke. And whether thei omitte theſame Engliſh Letany at any tyme in their proceſſions: &amp; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they haue had theſame Letanye as ofte as they were commaunded.</p>
            <p>Whether they haue put out of their churche bokes, this woorde Papa, and the name and ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uice of Thomas Becket, and prayers hauynge rubricies, conteyning Pardons or indulgences and all other ſuperſticious legendes &amp; prayers.</p>
            <p>Whether they bid the beades accordynge to the ordre preſcribed by our late ſouereigne lord kyng Henry the .viij.</p>
            <p>Whether they or any of them, haue been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their benefices by Simony, or by any other vnlaufull meanes.</p>
            <p>Whether in theyr maſſes they vſe not the collectes made for the Kyng, and make not ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall mencyon of hys Maieſties name in the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame.</p>
            <p>Whether they or any of theim, doo kepe mo benefices, and other Eccleſiaſticall promocions then they ought to doo, not hauynge ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient licences and diſpenſacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and howe many they ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, and theyr names. ,:,</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> (◆'◆) <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:12852:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether you knowe anye perſon, that is a letter of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of God, to be redde in Engliſh: So that it bee mekely, humbly, &amp; reuerently done, &amp; without diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baunce of the people, and by them that haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie thereto.</p>
               <p>Whether you knowe any perſon ſpirituall or temporall, which doeth let the woorde of God, to be preached, or that the Kinges Iniunctions ſhould not be duely executed.</p>
               <p>Whether any perſone hath obſtinately and maliciouſly, without a iuſte &amp; reaſonable cauſe, broken the laudable ceremonies of the Church, commaunded to be obſerued, or ſuperſticiouſly abuſed theſame: as in caſtynge of holy Water vpon theyr beddes and other places, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng about them holy breade, or makyng croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of woodde vpon Palme Sundaye, or bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng with the holy Candell, thinkyng therby to put awaye ſynnes, dryue awaye deuilles, drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and phantaſies, or puttynge truſte or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theſame ceremonies, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reas they be ordeined only to put vs in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of the benefites, whiche we haue recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by Chriſte.</p>
               <p>Whether any perſon ſpirituall or temporall, kepe the Church holy daye, and the dedication day, at any other tyme, then is appointed by the ordinaunce made in that behalfe by the Kinges Maieſtie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12852:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12852:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12852:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->Whether Matens, Maſſe, and Euenſong, be kept at due houres in the Churche.</p>
               <p>Whether any bee braulers, ſlaunderers, chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſcolders, and ſowers of diſcorde, betwene one perſone and another.</p>
               <p>Whether any bee common ſwearars, or blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers of the name of God.</p>
               <p>Whether any vſe, lewde, vnchaſt, vnhoneſt, &amp; filthy communicacion, ſonges or ballettes.</p>
               <p>Whether any doo vſe to common, Iangle or talke in the Churche, at the tyme of the diuine ſeruice, Preachyng, Readyng, or declaryng the worde of God.</p>
               <p>Whether any do obſtinatly kepe and defend any erronious opinion, contrary to the worde of God, and faith of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Whether any commit adultery, fornicacion, or inceſt, or bee common baudes, and receiuors of ſuche naughtie perſones.</p>
               <p>Whether you knowe any that vſe Charmes, Sorcery, Enchauntmentes, Witchecraft, ſothe ſaiyng, or any other like crafte inuented by the deuill.</p>
               <p>Whether you knowe any to be maried with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the degrees prohibited by the lawe of God, or that bee ſeparated and diuorced without a iuſte cauſe, approued by the law of God, and whether any ſuche haue maried again.</p>
               <p>Whether the Churche, Pulpit, and other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary thinges apperteinyng to theſame, be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficiently repaired.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12852:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->Whether you know any to haue made priuie contractes of Matrimony, not callyng twoo or moo thereunto.</p>
               <p>Whether any haue maried ſolempnely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bannes aſkyng.</p>
               <p>Whether you knowe any that haue taken v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon theim, the execution of any mannes teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or be admitted to the adminiſtracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the goodes of the dedde, whiche do not duely diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute theſame goodes, accordyng to the truſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto theim, and ſpecially ſuche goodes, as wer geuen and bequethed, or appointed to be diſtributed emong the poore people, repairyng of high waies, finding of poore ſcholars, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of poore maides.</p>
               <p>To what vſes and intentes, all ſuche gyftes and bequeſtes, of cattail, money, and other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as in tymes paſt wer made, for the findyng of tapers, candelles, or lampes, in the Churche, be now employed, and whether thei be embecil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and withholden, and by whom.</p>
               <p>Whether there bee any perſones, commonly enfamed of adultrie, fornicacion, common ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng, blaſphemyng the name of God, droncken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Simony, or other notorious crime, whom the biſhop, Archedeacon, or other his ordinary, for fauor or feare, haue not corrected accordyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gly, although thei haue been ſundery tymes pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſented, and detected in viſitacion, or otherwyſe lawfully accuſed.</p>
               <p>Whether there be any other primars, vſed by
<pb facs="tcp:12852:8"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
them that doo not vnderſtande Latyn, then the Englyſh Prymar, ſethfurth by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie: And whither they that vnderſtand Latin, do vſe any other then the latin primar ſettfurth by lyke aucthoritie.</p>
               <p>Whether there be any other Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer taught in any ſchole, within the realme, then that which is ſetfurth by the kynges Maieſtie.</p>
               <p>Whether they knowe any alienacion of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, tenementes, iewelles or goodes, perteyning to the Churche.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For chauntry Prieſtes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether they be reſidente on their Chauntries.</p>
               <p>Whether they be aydinge and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtynge the perſone or Vicar of the Churche, that they be of in the miniſtracion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sacramentes, and diuine ſeruice accordingly.</p>
               <p>Whether they kepe and perfourme all ſuche dooles and diſtribucions to the pore, and other dedes of Charitie, as they are bounde by theyr foundacions to do.</p>
               <p>Whether thei be of euil name, fame, or vnho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt conuerſacion, fighters, ſwearars, dronckar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, or incontinent lyuers.</p>
               <p>Item, what benefices and how many they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, beſides their Chauntryes, and by what title they do kepe theſame.</p>
               <p>¶ <hi>Richardus Grafton Regius Impreſſor excudebat. Cum Priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
